Good morning, my name is Dan Margulies, I'm filling in for Rabbi
Linzer while he's away. Today is August 25th, it's the 21st of
אב, Av, and our דף daf today is going to be פ"ו,
Pei Vav, we're starting about 20 lines from the bottom on פ"ה
עמוד ב' Pei Hei Amud Bet where it says אמר רבא. Amar
Rava. We have been discussing the question of how to calculate שבת,
shevet, that is, how do you calculate the amount of compensation a
person receives based on an injury for the amount of time that
they're going to be off of work or that they'll be unable
to do their normal job. And so far we had seen that
the discussion centers around basically the idea that a person will be
unable to do the work that they used to do and now
they have to be assessed at the value of a type of
work that they're able to do now that they've received this injury.
For example, a person who could have been any sort of, any
sort of work, now suppose their hand has been injured, at least
in Talmudic times that would mean a person could probably not do
very many jobs that you would need both hands for, so you're
assessed at the level of a שומר קישואין, shomer kishuin, someone who
sits and watches a pumpkin patch, because that's a type of work
where you need to walk around but you don't need to use
your hands.
And if it was someone who had been injured in the leg,
they have to be assessed at the rate that a person who's
a שומר shomer at the gate of the city, because a toll
collector is someone who just sits in one place, they don't have
to even walk around, so if you've injured your foot then that
would be the level you're assessed at. And if a person had
become blind from this injury, then they would be assessed based on
their ability to grind wheat, they could sit at the millstone, מטחינה
בריחיים, matchina bareichayim, but at the same time they would not have
to move around at all and they could do a job even
that doesn't require the use of their eyes. And the גמרא Gemara
had said if a person became deaf based on this injury then
you pay דמי כולו, dmei kulo, you pay the entire value, why?
Because, because,
sorry, I'm jumping ahead a little bit. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבא קטע ידו נותן לו דמי ידו
ושבת רואים אותו כאילו הוא שומר קישואין. Amar Rava keta yado noten
lo dmei yado veshevet ro'im oto ke'ilu hu shomer kishuin. Sorry, we've
got farther than I thought we did. We got up to where
it says בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, right? Okay, so we're actually more
like 15 lines up from the bottom. Okay, so בעי רבא, ba'ei
Rava, Rava asked, קטע ידו ולא אמדוהו, keta yado velo imduhu, so
what if a person severed someone else's hand and the בית דין
Beit Din did not get a chance to assess the damage yet?
Okay, step one. שיבר רגלו ולא אמדוהו, shiber raglo velo imduhu, and
then he went and broke the guy's foot
and they did not assess the damage yet. סימא את עינו ולא
אמדוהו, sima et eino velo imduhu, and then he blinded him and
then they didn't assess the damage yet. ולבסוף חרשו, ulvasof hersho, and
then he made him deaf, מהו? mahu? מי אמרינן כיון דלא אמדוהו
בחדא
אמדנא סגיא ליה ויהיב ליה דמי כולו? mi amrinan keivan d'lo imduhu
bechada amdana sagya lei vehayiv lei dmei kulo? So maybe you'll say,
בחדא מחתא, bechada machta, maybe you'll say that because they didn't get
a chance to actually pay yet or they didn't get a chance
to actually assess the damage yet, then at that point since they
only do one assessment at the end based on all four injuries,
you should just pay one lump sum. או דלמא חדא חדא אמדינא
ויהבינא ליה? o dilma chada chada amdina vehavina lei? Or maybe each
injury has to be assessed on its own accord and then he
has to pay four separate payments? So what's the נפקא מינה, nafka
mina, meaning what should be the difference? If it's the same injury
it should end up having the same payment either way. So we're
going to see. Yeah, exactly. So you know, we were discussing that
there's נזק, nezek, then it comes along with everything else. And then
we said if there's like, you know, one thing
individually and then you pay individually like צער tza'ar or בושת boshet
or whatever. Right. But can you couple things without נזק? nezek? Let's
say he's now too embarrassed. So that's going to be coming up
on today's דף daf and we're going to see there're going to
be cases that we're going to deal with that are going to
deal with like just בושת boshet and not נזק nezek and things
like that. For example, if you publicly stupid-ify him? Yeah, for sure,
meaning any of them could be paid based on the assessment of
the situation individually. But it's not just נזק, nezek, it's not just
five things or one thing, it could be two things. Right, it
could be two or three, right, depending on the circumstance. Okay, so
נפקא מינה, nafka mina, what's the נפקא מינה nafka mina between if
it was one assessment or four separate assessments? דמשכחת לה צער ובושת
דכל חדא וחדא demishkachat la tza'ar uvoshet dechol chada vechada because צער
tza'ar and בושת boshet are going to be different for each one.
That is, the שבת shevet and the ריפוי ripuy in the end
are going to work out the same because the amount of devaluation
of each one is going to add up to the point of
the next one, so in the end it's going to cover the
full spectrum. But צער tza'ar and בושת, boshet, each injury is going
to incur more pain and suffering and each injury is going to
incur more embarrassment in terms of how this person presents in public
arena. And therefore צער tza'ar and בושת, boshet, if you assess them
individually it's going to compound to actually a higher amount of צער
tza'ar and a higher amount of בושת. boshet. דהאי דנזק וריפוי ושבת
כל חדא וחדא לא יהבינא ליה, dehai d'nezek veripuy veshevet kol chada
vechada lo havina lei, דכיון דיהיב ליה דמי כולו כמאן דקטליה דמי.
dekeivan deyaiv lei dmei kulo keman dekatleh dami. So and the fact
that you're if you pay
so for the other three, that is שבת, shevet, ריפוי, ripuy, and
נזק, nezek, the fact that you pay for the whole thing, that
is, the person has been injured to the point of of a
of a full full assessment. So in that sense you're saying okay,
you're paying כמאן דקטליה דמי. keman de-katleh damei. It's like you've killed
the person. That is not obviously kill the person, we don't let
you pay if you've killed someone, but the sense is that since
you've impaired their ability to work, the שבת shevet is like you're
paying the entire person's ability to earn a living. The ריפוי rippui
is a very significant medical expense. And the נזק nezek obviously you've
damaged them in an extensive way such that a person's value in
the slave market will be incredibly severely reduced. So that's also like
that you would have to pay almost like to the sense the
whole person's worth. Obviously a person doesn't have a worth but in
the sense we have to have an assessment for that for נזק.
nezek. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ובהא יהיב ליה דמי כולה.
ve-ha yahiv leh damei kuleh. So if you pay the money for
the person's entire self, צער ובושת מי חזי כל חד וחדא יהיב
ליה? tza'ar ve-boshet mi chazi kol chad ve-chada yahiv leh? Okay, so
then what about צער ובושת tza'ar ve-boshet because the whole point was
that צער ובושת tza'ar ve-boshet are going to be compounded further. You're
actually going to end up paying more if you do separate assessments
than if you do the whole thing. דכל חדא וחדא יהיב דהא
הוי ליה צער ובושת de-kol chada ve-chada yahiv de-ha havei leh tza'ar
ve-boshet
because צער ובושת tza'ar ve-boshet are going to be separate. ואי תימא
לומר כיון דלא אמדוהו, ve-im tima lomar keivan de-lo amduhu, so if
you'll say that the reason why is because they didn't get a
chance to assess in between each of the injuries, וקיהיב ליה דמי
כולה בהדי הדדי, ve-ka yahiv leh damei kuleh bahadi hadadi, and then
you could pay one lump sum all at the end. But אמדוהו,
amduhu, if they had assessed the value in between each injury but
the person just didn't get a chance to pay it yet, then
what do you say? So מהו? mahu? מי אמרינן כיון
דאמדוהו חדא וחדא בעי למיתב ליה? mi amrinan keivan de-amduhu chada ve-chada
ba'ei le-meitav leh? Maybe because each injury was individually assessed, he has
to give it to him each one separately? או דילמא כיון דלא
שלים יהיב ליה דמי כולה? o dilma keivan de-lo shalim yahiv leh
damei kuleh? So then
or maybe the alternative is that if the person didn't pay yet,
then there's no need to pay each one individually, rather you can
combine them into the one lump sum and then the צער ובושת
tza'ar ve-boshet are going to accordion collapse on each other because they'll
be double counted. So the גמרא Gemara ends תיקו. teiku. That means
all of רבא's Rava questions about this have been left unresolved. That
is רבא Rava presented two different possibilities. Either we should assess צער
ובושת tza'ar ve-boshet in particular should be assessed based on individual damages
if there was no assessment in between, or maybe even if there
was assessment in between, as long as the payment didn't come through,
they should be assessed individually, or maybe they should just be assessed
all together from the beginning to the end and ignoring all the
details in the middle. Yes? Does that mean if he's paying just
the entire value, he's not going to pay for humiliation and pain
at all? He will pay צער ובושת tza'ar ve-boshet for the the
sum total of the injuries, but not for each one individually. The
גמרא's Gemara point is that if we would assess how much צער
ובושת tza'ar ve-boshet were involved for each of these four injuries, the
the sum of all four would be more than if you would
assess it each one by itself. So because presumably a person gets
in one accident and they have all four injuries at the same
time, the amount of בושת boshet for example that they'll feel or
the amount of pain that they feel at one moment or for
that one period of time is going to be less than if
they went through four individual injuries. The גמרא Gemara ends תיקו תיקו
teiku teiku is an unresolved question. That is רבא's Rava question was
left unanswered. Interestingly enough, and the רמב"ם Rambam does this consistently, the
answer what we have to פוסק הלכה posek halacha based on a
תיקו teiku is usually that we're kind of in a case of
doubt. And in a monetary case we would say okay, you can't
use the conclusion of the תיקו teiku to take someone else's money
away. But that means אי תפס לא מפקינן. ei tafas lo mafkinan.
If the person trying to claim this money had already grabbed it,
had already taken it from the person who he thought owed them,
then you can't take it back from him because he has a
certain ground to stand up. Strangely enough, the ראש Rosh in the
back here actually פוסק, posek, he thinks which side actually makes sense,
if you take a look at the ראש, Rosh, the ראש Rosh
thinks it makes more sense to assess each one individually, it's right
at the end of סימן ה siman heh in the ראש. Rosh.
It just does to me, too. But it makes sense. So, but
the תוספות יום טוב Tosafot Yom Tov and the פלפלא חריפתא Pilpula
Charifta says, how can the ראש Rosh just decide for himself to
decide a question that the גמרא Gemara leaves unanswered? That is fine,
it might make sense to a certain amount of, it might make
sense, but it doesn't give you the right to פוסק. pasken. If
it's a תיקו, teiku, תיקו teiku means it's left unresolved. So it's
תיקו? teiku? Okay,
so it's an interesting question and we have to see how how
different ראשונים Rishonim approach, what does it mean the תיקו? teiku? Okay.
Also that that means you're not making a distinction between if between
each having been done separately as opposed to the person had an
accident and all happened? Well obviously it's not an accident, obviously we're
talking about a case where a person injured someone else, but the
point is whether it was four individual acts of violence, separate incidents,
or or one all at once, right? I still don't get
the נזק nezek part, meaning I still the sum of
the נזיקין nezikin is not is greater. how
much would he be a legless slave versus a leg, a legged
slave? And then it's going to be a person who is blind
and has no legs compared to a person who is seeing and
has no legs. So then that's one more step. And then now
we're going to go from here to here, so then one, two,
three, they're all three going to add up to the whole thing.
Correct, but they're each one going to add up to the whole
thing. Right, because I did it separate times. But let's say he
did it all at once? Correct, but the נזק nezek adds up.
The point of how נזק nezek is assessed is that the נזק,
nezek, the first נזק nezek gets you from here to here, second
one here to here, third one here to here, so then the
whole thing if it were to be assessed all at once is
going to cover the same thing. No, then the difference is how
much is a slave worth? Well, as I'm doing it separate times,
also along the way, how much is the slave worth? I still,
what I'm saying is the last... But the point is that the
evaluation of, but that's the point, is that the way this slave
market at least calculates those values is that it's going to work
out evenly in the end. You're saying how much is a whole
slave worth? Right, right, so then in the end the fourth one
that is, if you made him deaf, then he's worth nothing. And
the idea is that the, then the slave who is also at
that point a blind, deaf, legless, handless slave is basically worth nothing.
So what's the difference? Right. No, no, but my point is let's
say five different times, I'm saying you get the fifth one plus
the fourth one and plus the third one plus is this plus
this plus this plus this is this. I understand, but it's done
incrementally. Okay, to me, it was over the course of 15 years,
so you get at the end, at the last time, you get
everything. No, he doesn't get everything. He gets the difference between this
one and this one. And the previous time he got the difference
between this one and this one. Each, it's incremental. I know, I
understand, but it's done different times, what I'm trying to say is
that everyone knows that it happened, so he should get, each assessment
has a different starting point. I know, that's my point. It ends
up at the same place. Michael, maybe we could talk about it
afterwards, I'm not sure I understand the question. Okay. But it's at
the same place, then what's the difference? It's like saying 5 plus
4 plus 3 plus 2 plus 1, but 5 plus 4 plus
3 plus 2 plus 1 is more. But it's not 5 plus
4. It's 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1, and it's 3
plus 1. Yes it is. That's exactly the point. So what's the
question? It's like 5 minus 1 you get to 4. No, you
get 1. Or you get the 4 minus 1 you get to
the 3. Wait, either way, we're doing the same thing. Right. It's
going to end up at the same place, what's the question being
asked? The question being asked is about צער tzaar and בושת. boshet.
That is, each individual injury is going to have its own level
of embarrassment and its own level of צער, tzaar, which in total
are going to add up to more than the amount of צער
tzaar and בושת boshet if all of the injuries were assessed at
once. And that's because a person suffers a pain based on each
injury. If you're in pain, of your whole body all at once
is going to be less than each individual... What you're saying is
it's going to end up at the same place. That's about נזק.
nezek. נזק, nezek, ריפוי, ripui, and שבת shevet are going to add
up to the same. We're on the fourth-to-the-last line of פה עמוד
ב. peh amud bet. The גמרא Gemara says: בעי רבא. Baei Rava.
רבא Rava asked a question. That is, we already had רבה's Rabbah's
questions, now we have רבא. Rava. And it's going to come back,
we're going to see the גמרא Gemara is going to address this
later. So, בעי רבא. Baei Rava. שבת הפוחתו בדמים מהו? Shevet hapocheto
bidamim mahu?
What is a case of שבת, shevet, that is, amount paid for
time off of work, that reduces a person's value? This is a
little bit of a strange, a strange formulation. Look in רש"י: Rashi:
הכינו מכה שהוא צריך לשבת ממלאכתו וסופו להיות שלם כבראשונה. Hikino makah
shehu tzarich leshevet mimalachto vesofo lihyot shalem kevarishonah. That is, a person
got an injury such that they have to take time off of
work, but the injury will heal. And therefore the presumption is that
on the one hand, you're not really paying נזק nezek because the
נזק, nezek, the injury, is going to heal, but at the same
time, how do you assess the שבת shevet in that case? Because
we thought the whole point of שבת shevet was that for the
rest of this person's life he's going to be unable to do
this kind of work, he's going to have to do a lesser
kind of work, so you have to compensate him in that way.
But here, the person is going to be able to go back
to work. He's going to have two weeks off of work and
then he's going to be fine. So that's the question. Okay. So,
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? כגון שהכהו על ידו וצמתה ידו. Kegon shehikahu
al yado vetzamtah yado.
So suppose someone hit someone else on the hand and it got
a horrible bruise or it got a horrible scab or something, וסופו
לחזור, vesofo lachzor, and in the end it's going to heal. It
might take a month, it might take two months, but in the
end it's going to be fine. Okay. So מאי? mai? כיון דסופו
לחזור לא יהיב ליה ולא מידי? Keivan desofo lachzor lo yahiv leh
velo midi?
Maybe because it's going to grow back, it's going to heal, then
he doesn't have any obligation to pay him for שבת shevet at
all, because fine, even though you're off of work for now, but
you're going to go back to your original job. Okay. Or, או
דילמא השתא מיהת אפחתה? o dilma hashta mihat apchateh?
So no, right now you reduced his earning power. That is, at
least for these two months he's going to have time off of
work. So this is the question of what שבת shevet is to
begin with. That is, this whole time at least the משנה Mishnah
was still unclear. What does שבת shevet mean? שבת, shevet, does it
mean the time off of work because of the injury, or does
it mean
a lifelong
reduction... I don't know, we have to ask that question. So רבא
Rava, *Rava* asked a question, so we're going to see. Meaning they're
two very different possi- of lifelong thing. I always thought potentially temporary.
Why? I cut off your hand, so now I'm never going to
be able to do a job. How is the תורה *Torah* speaking
about it? Meaning תורה *Torah* says, you know, I hit you, whatever,
a bruise, a כוייה *kviyah* is not necessarily something that's... Okay, so
until this point at least, the examples in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
had been a severed hand or a broken leg which at their
time which they didn't have the kinds of bone setting that we
have, a broken leg meant it was going to heal wrong and
you weren't going to be able to walk anyway, or being blinded,
a permanent injury that's going to fundamentally affect your earning power. But
is that what the תורה *Torah* is talking about? So the תורה
*Torah* doesn't say anything. The תורה *Torah* says רק שבתו יתן *rak
shivto yiten*. משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* too. משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says קטעה את
ידו *kita et yado*. קטעה את ידו *kita et yado*, you cut
off his hand. So we're going to have to see. So רבא
Rava. *Rava* asks this question. It's a very good question that is
really getting to the core of what is שבת shevet, *shevet* actually
compensation for? Is it for lost wages during the time for your
recovery or is it lost wages because you've fundamentally been altered in
terms of your earning power? Okay. So תא שמע ta shema. *tah
shema*: המכה אביו ואמו *hamakeh aviv ve'imo*.
What if a person hits their parents ולא עשה בהן חבורה *velo
asa bahen chaburah*? But it didn't leave a bruise. We know the
הלכה halacha *halacha* is מכה אביו ואמו מות יומת *makeh aviv ve'imo
mot yumot*. If you injure your parent in such a way that
it does leave a bruise, then that's a capital crime because even
though it doesn't actually kill your parents, but the fact that you've
injured them so substantially is such a disrespect to your parents that
that's considered to be a capital crime. I must be very thick
because תורה *Torah* says ואם יקום והתהלך בחוץ על משענתו ונקה המכה
רק שבתו יתן ורפא ירפא *ve'im yakum vehithalech bachutz al mishanto venikah
hamakeh rak shivto yiten verapo yerapeh*. So obviously he's getting back. ונקה
המכה *nikah hamakeh* for capital punishment.
That's what that פסוק *pasuk* is saying. But what's this והתהלך *ve'hithalech*,
you're walking על משענתו *al mishanto* on your own. Right, so that
means that in a case where a person was injured mortally but
recovered enough to be able to walk, that means it wasn't considered
to be a mortal wound. That means this injury,
if I hit you and then you have internal bleeding and three
weeks later you die, I could still be put to death for
that because I injured you in such a way that the injury
killed you even though it wasn't right then. What this is saying
is if a person gets up after the injury and then a
month later dies, it was proof that the injury was not a
mortal wound at the time of the injury and therefore the person
who caused the damage is not a murderer. And that's what that
פסוק *pasuk* is about. And then the שבת shevet *shevet* is... שבת
shevet *shevet* is about how much you pay for someone's off work.
רק שבתו יתן ורפא ירפא *rak shivto yiten verapo yerapeh*. He died,
so you still pay him for the שבת shevet. *shevet*? No, it's
saying if he didn't die, then he has שבת shevet *shevet* or...
But still he's incapacitated. He was incapacitated from his injuries. Exactly, he
was unable to work. It doesn't seem like the פשט *pshat*. It
doesn't have to be the פשט *pshat*, it has to be what
the הלכה halakhah *halacha* is. Okay. תא שמע Ta shema: *tah shema*:
המכה אביו ואמו ולא עשה בהן חבורה *hamakeh aviv ve'imo velo asa
bahen chaburah*. If you hit your parents in such a way that
did not leave a bruise. החובל בחבירו ביום הכפורים *hachovel bechavero beyom
hakippurim* or if you punch someone on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, חייב
hayyav, בכולם *chayav bekulam*,
you're obligated to pay all five things. We know if you punch
someone on שבת shevet *Shabbat*, if you injure someone on שבת shevet.
*Shabbat*, or if you hit your parents in such a way that
it does leave a bruise, because those are capital crimes we would
say קים ליה בדרבה מיניה *kim leh d'rabah mineh*, you would be
exempt from the monetary obligation. But punching someone on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* because you're חייב hayyav כרת *chayav karet* or hitting your parents
in such a way that does not leave a bruise, you would
be obligated to pay all five. Ah, what does it sound like?
It sounds like if you hit your parents and it didn't leave
a bruise you would still have to pay all five. That is
an injury that does not leave a permanent mark of any kind
then still you would pay שבת shevet. *shevet*. That is the injury,
even a temporary injury, would require שבת shevet *shevet*. So that's what
it sounds like from that ברייתא braita, *braita*. Okay. האי ולא עשה
בהן חבורה היכי דמי *hai velo asa bahen chaburah heichi dami*? But
what case is it that does not leave a bruise? לאו כגון
שהכהו על ידו וסופו לחזור *lav kegon shehikahu al yado vesofo lachazor*
and it says חייב hayyav. בכולם *chayav bekulam*. So doesn't it sound
like a contradiction? Because it sounds like what injury doesn't leave a
permanent injury would be if you hit them on the hand and
eventually it's going to grow back and it said חייב hayyav, בכולם
*chayav bekulam*, you're obligated in all five. אמרי Amri הכא במאי עסקינן
*amri hacha bemai askinan*? No, this is what we're talking about. כגון
שחרשו *kegon shechersho*. It wasn't that you hit your parent on the
hand and then it healed, it was that you injured them in
such a way that there was no blood to begin with, that
is you made your parent deaf, you injured your parent in such
a way that it made them lose their hearing. ולא עשה בו
חבורה *velo asa bo chaburah*. And does that really not leave a
wound? והאמר רבא Rava החרשו לאביו נהרג *veha'amar rava hacheresho le'aviv neherag*.
But רבא Rava. *Rava* said, and this again we're trying to answer
רבא Rava *Rava*'s question to begin with so it's very good that
it was רבא *Rava* who we're talking about, so if you make
your father deaf you'll be executed for that. Why? לפי שאי אפשר
לחרישה בלא חבורה טיפת דם נפלה לו באזנו *lefi she'efshar lehacharisha velo
chaburah tipat dam nafla leh be'ozneh*. Because the way a person becomes
deaf in that kind of an injury is that a drop of
blood goes into the ear and that's what causes the deafness. And
so therefore now the question becomes basically what they're describing is a
kind of an internal... bleeding it sounds like. That is, something happened
internally which involved bleeding and that's what caused the injury that results
in loss of hearing. Interestingly enough though, it seems to be somewhat
of a מחלוקת machloket *machloket* about whether or not internal bleeding counts
for this question of the capital crime of injuring your parent or
not. The bit of an interesting extension discussion also question of what
מלאכה *melacha* is it to cause someone to have a bruise on
שבת shevet. *Shabbat*. It's I think maybe even a three-way מחלוקת machloket
*machloket* in the ראשונים Rishonim *rishonim*. One possibility is שוחט *shochet*, it's
a תולדה דשוחט *tolada de-shochet*. שוחט *shochet* means to kill an animal.
צובע *tzoveia* as Michael said. Oh wait one second we're going to
get to that. So one possibility is שוחט *shochet*, that is if
I kill an animal and the blood obviously drains out, so if
I punch someone and it causes the blood to group together in
that place, that's kind of like שוחט *shochet*. Or maybe it's צובע
*tzoveia* as Michael said, it's like dyeing because you've turned their skin
from one color to a different color. Or maybe it's דש *dash*
because we know that the מלאכה *melacha* of דש *dash* which is
threshing, removing the kernels from the wheat stalk also becomes applied to
things like milking a cow or squeezing a fruit that so too
punching a person in such a way that it causes a bruise
is drawing the blood out of their flesh in such a way
that it's kind of like squeezing out a fruit. So those are
at least three possibilities for what מלאכה חובל chovel *melacha chovel* is.
The גמרא Gemara *gemara* takes it for granted almost that חובל בחבירו
*chovel be-chavero* on שבת shevet *Shabbat* is one of the מלאכות *melachot*,
but it's not clear which one it is. Okay. So רבא *Rava*
had said that causing your parents to lose their hearing is something
that you would be killed for because it's impossible for the hearing
to be lost without a drop of blood being dislodged. So that
couldn't be the case we're talking about because we have to be
talking about a case where there was an injury that a person
could cause their parents which does not leave any kind of a
bruise and does not involve any kind of bleeding, but at the
same time is temporary such to prove that there's such a thing
as שבת shevet *shevet* even for a temporary injury. Okay. אלא הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון שגילחו *ela hacha be-mai askinan kigon she-gilcho*. It was
a case where a person shaved his father's head. Okay so we're
going to see. So גילחו *gilcho*? מהדר הדר והיינו בהיינו *mehadar hadar
ve-hainu be-hainu*.
So the hair is going to grow back. That's what you're telling
me that that's an injury? Okay. So אמרי הכא במאי עסקינן כגון
שסכו נשרא *amrei hacha be-mai askinan kigon she-sacho nashra*. No, he used
some kind of a depilatory cream or resin that burns the skin
and burns off the hair and it burns off the hair permanently.
Nowadays we have things like laser hair removal, things like that that
are permanent hair removal. Okay. So if it's permanent hair removal then
it's a permanent injury. Okay, so then what how can you make
it all other five though? It's still, fine, you'll say that that's
some kind of a נזק nezek. *nezek*, you've damaged this person in
some way. So צער דאית ליה כרטופני בראשיה *tzaar de-it lei kartufnei
be-reishei*, the person had fissures or cracks in his skin on his
head and therefore when you put the cream
that burned in the
and it causes burning because of those scars on the head. So
ריפוי *ripui*, what about ריפוי *ripui*, the healing cost? דבעי אסויי *de-baei
asuyei* is because he needs to go to the doctor for that
because once you have cracks in your
the skin on your scalp and then you put this depilatory cream
and it burns, you have to go to the doctor. Okay שבת
shevet *shevet*, what about שבת shevet *shevet*? Meaning what work do you
lose from having become bald and having this injury on your head?
דהוה מרקיד בי כובי *de-hava markid bei kuvei* because he was a
juggler or dancer in the in the bar, that he was some
kind of a jester or some kind of a comedian type. So
in that case so why? דבעי מחוי גוני ארישא ולא מחוי מהני
כרטופני *de-baei mechavei gunei a-reisha velo mechavei me-hanei kartufnei* because he has
to go and wag his head around in front of people as
part of I guess the way they would dance back then and
therefore he can't do that because he has these injuries to his
scalp. So and בושת boshet, אין in, לך בושת boshet, גדול gadol
מזה *boshet ein lach boshet gadol mi-zeh* and forcing someone who is
not naturally going bald to go bald prematurely is very embarrassing. Well,
unless it's the baldness itself.
Well, obviously well there are אחרונים *achronim* who point that out, which
is to say where'd we ever hear that baldness is embarrassing? Everybody
you know very many men and very many women frankly lose their
hair at some point and that's just natural. It's natural to age
gracefully. What's not what's embarrassing is if you lose your hair prematurely,
if you lose your hair all at once when you weren't expecting
it. To take someone who has a full head of hair or
even a partial head of hair and take it all off overnight,
that would be very embarrassing. Obviously depends on the cultural context as
well, that is if you live in a culture where people regularly
shave their heads or things like that and people have very short
hair, it may not be as embarrassing, the בושת boshet *boshet* might
be relatively minor. At least in חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*'s culture. But our
question, the point is שבת shevet *shevet*. Here the שבת Shabbat *shevet*
is assessed why? He gets שבת *shevet* because his job was to
be a jester in the bar and he can't do that job
anymore, at least for a while. So it sounds like a temporary
thing, obviously it's going to heal. That is the hair is not
going to... but it's a depilatory. Okay. So the hair is not
going to grow back, but the ability to shake his head around
is because of the כרטופני *kartufnei*, is because of the cracks in
his scalp. which are going to which are going to heal. So
that's one possibility, but the the question of the hair is a
good point, it's not it's not clear, but the point is that
the בושת boshet. also is a set based on the job that
he has. And this becomes a question again in the ראש... Rosh...
שבת, sorry. שבת is calculated based on the job he has now.
It's not just based on the job you could do once you
were injured, it's also a comparison between your current job that you're
unable to do now compared to something something else. So he still
gets paid as a cucumber watcher, but it's just that well I
don't even know if he's the only he could do many jobs
he probably needs to be getting paid above the cucumber watcher. No,
I'm saying he's still his שבת is you pay him as that.
No, we saw that for different types of injuries you might pay
a different amount based on what they're able to do. Right, but
you pay some sort of low level presumably has to be some
kind of a low level presumably he's paid more and which is
why he's getting compensated if he's got a job that paid less
you wouldn't correct correct. So I don't know it doesn't say here
what job he would assess him for, but presumably the case of
the cucumber watchmen was because he had his hand cut off so
he couldn't do any kind of manual labor. Here this is someone
who had a skilled a skilled kind of labor
that required a more creative creative type job and now maybe he's
going to have to get a work as a manual laborer that's
going to pay less than than his skilled job. It's interesting just
to note that sort of variable subjective component of שבת. Okay. Okay.
אין הכי נמי בושת גדול מזה. ein hachi nami boshet gadol mizeh.
Okay. ומילתא דבעיא ליה לרבה פשיטא ליה
לאביי
להכי ולרבא
להכי. u'milta d'ba'alei le'Rabbah p'shita leh le'Abaye l'hachis u'le'Rava l'hachis.
Meaning this was all a question that Rabbah had. Rabbah didn't know
whether or not you should have שבת for an injury that was
going to heal. But what was a question for Rabbah was obvious
to Abaye one way and was obvious to Rava the other way.
That is Rava and Abaye one generation after Rabbah and רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. So Rava and Abaye have a big מחלוקת machloket about
something that their teacher Rabbah had a question about. So obviously I
mean you can imagine that this would happen, they're sitting in ישיבה
yeshiva and the ראש ישיבה rosh yeshiva asks a question and he
says I don't really know I kind of see both sides of
it and the two top students each pick a side and they
become invested in it. So it's just like an interesting interesting point.
Okay. So Rava and Abaye why? דאיתמר הכהו על ידו וצמתה וסופה
לחזור. de'itmar hikehu al yado v'tzimta v'sofo lachzor. What about a case
where a person hit someone on the hand and it got some
kind of a swelling or bruise in such a way that it
was unusable, but then it would heal
eventually. אביי אמר נותן לו שבת גדולה ושבת קטנה. Abaye amar noten
lo shevet gedola u'shevet ketana. He pays a large שבת and a
small שבת. Look in רש״י Rashi because otherwise we would not understand
what he's talking about. שבת גדולה דמי ידו. shevet gedola d'mei yado.
שבת גדולה shevet gedola sounds like it means what we've been calling
נזק. nezek That is the fact that you will never be able
to use this limb. נזק nezek. is you were devalued on the
slave market and we discussed yesterday how the devaluation on the slave
market takes into account the amount of work a person would be
able to do over a lifetime using that limb. So שבת גדולה
shevet gedola sounds like the
lifelong lifelong change based on what we've been calling נזק. nezek שבת
קטנה כל ימים שיפול למשכב ורואין אותו כאילו הוא
שומר קישואין. shevet ketana kol yamim sheyipol l'mishkav v'ro'in oto k'ilu hu
shomer kishu'in. Temporary loss of labor and we assess at that minimum
wage level based on the injury to the hand he has to
do. So שבת גדולה shevet gedola
becomes an interesting question. Why? Because it seems like the way Abaye
conceptualizes what we've been calling נזק nezek is fundamentally is basically the
same idea as שבת. שבת is the amount you reduction of your
earning power over a lifetime based on the permanent part of the
injury and over the short term in terms of the part of
injury that's going to heal. So both of those are each part
of שבת. The משנה Mishnah had used the term נזק nezek comparison
to שבת interesting. Also to note part of the question here is
how much are we comparing חובל to נזקי ממון. nizkei mamon. נזקי
ממון nizkei mamon we only assess נזק nezek the amount of damage
caused. Here because we have all five things it actually becomes interesting
to compare each of them to each other and Abaye seems to
compare what we've been calling נזק nezek to שבת because שבת is
also a time off of work. The way we think about that
is is reduction of earning power even for the נזק nezek as
well. You could imagine a human being has all sorts of value
beyond their ability to work. Nonetheless the work is what we can
assess in court in a reasonable way. Okay so רבא אמר אינו
נותן לו אלא דמי שבתו שבכל יום ויום. Rava amar eino noten
lo ela d'mei shivto shebechol yom va'yom. Rava says you only pay
שבת for each day and day. That means a temporary loss of
what Abaye called שבת קטנה. shevet ketana. That is Rava never heard
of שבת גדולה. shevet gedola. Rava heard of נזק nezek and he
thinks of them as two separate things. So obviously נזק nezek is
something that only applies if there's a permanent damage and שבת is
something you pay for temporary. So אתמר הקוטע יד עבד עברי של
חבירו. it'mar hakohtea yad eved Ivri shel chaveiro. What if a person
and now we have to go back in time a long time
what if you chop off an עבד עברי's eved Ivri hand? עבד
עברי... eved Ivri... is obligated to work for someone, but he doesn't
actually is not owned by anyone. He owns himself. He's a free
person in a sense, but he's an indentured
servant. עבד עברי של חבירו. eved ivri shel chavero. אביי אמר נותן
לו שבת גדולה לעבד ושבת קטנה לרב. Abaye amar noten lo shevet
gedola la'eved veshevet ketana larav. You pay שבת גדולה, shevet gedola, that
is for the injury, you pay to the עבד, eved, and to
the master you pay the amount of time that he won't be
able to work because he's, he has a contractual agreement to work
for the master. So who owns the rights to his labor for
the temporary period of time when he's recovering? Was the, was the
master. Okay. רבא אמר הכל ינתן לעבד. Rava amar hakol yinaten la'eved.
According to רבא, everything goes to the slave because the evaluation of
נזיקין nezikin is not about who bought the rights to your labor,
it's about whether or not you can earn the money for yourself.
וילקח בהן קרקע, veyilakach bahen karka, and he, the slave, should buy
land with that money, והרב אוכל פירות, veharav ochel peirot, and the
master is allowed to eat the produce of the field. That is,
the type of relationship that the master has in terms of the
ownership of the work of the עבד eved is not that he
owns the עבד's eved labor, he's allowed to be אוכל פירות. ochel
peirot. He can get the benefits from the labor. So the same
financial model we know by or in a marriage as well: who
owns the land compared to who can get the fruits, get the
produce of that labor, so too is the relationship of the עבד
עברי eved ivri to the master. The master does not own the
work itself, he only owns the פירות, peirot, the fruits of the
labor. Okay. So this is מחלוקת machloket between אביי Abaye and רבא.
So פשיטא פיחת אצל עצמו ואצל רבו לא פיחת? p'shita pichat eitzel
atzmo ve'eitzel rabbo lo pichat? But what? He didn't, he wasn't devalued
for his master, he was only devalued for himself? It's a question
on רבא's שיטה. shita. Okay. היכי דמי דפסקי' לריש אודנא או לריש
נחירא? heichi dami depaskei lerish udna o lerish nechira? Now maybe it
was that his earlobe was cut or his nostril was cut, and
therefore that's when all of the נזק nezek, goes to him himself.
הכל לעצמו. hakol le'atzmo. It goes to
him. פיחת אצל רבו פלוגתא דאביי ורבא. pichat eitzel rabbo plugta de'Abaye
veRava. But if he was injured in a place where it's going
to affect his ability to work directly, well then that's going to
be מחלוקת between אביי Abaye and רבא. But that is, everyone agrees
that if even אביי Abaye will agree to רבא that if the
injury was in a place that doesn't actually affect his ability to
work, then the only thing that the owner is losing out on,
not owner, the slave master, is losing out on is the פירות
peirot and therefore he should get the נזיקין nezikin money, buy a
piece of land, and the פירות peirot will go to the master.
Okay. We're in the middle of פ"ו עמוד א'. peh vav amud
aleph. בושת הכל לפי המבייש והמתבייש. boshet hakol lefi hamivayesh vehamitbayesh.
Mishnah has said that בושת, boshet. embarrassment, is assessed based on everything
is assessed based on who is the מבייש, mivayesh, who
did the embarrassing, and המתבייש, hamitbayesh, the person who got embarrassed. So
we have to see, so it's very subjective. So מני מתניתין? mani
matnitin? לא רבי מאיר ולא רבי יהודה אלא רבי שמעון היא. lo
Rabbi Meir velo Rabbi Yehuda ella Rabbi Shimon hi. So who is
our Mishnah like? It's not like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, not like
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it must be רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So
we're going to see a discussion of the three-way מחלוקת between these
three תנאים. tannaim. Okay, דתנן, detnan, the ברייתא, braita the ברייתא braita
says, וכולן רואין אותם כאילו
הם בני חורין שירדו מנכסיהם שהם בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב דברי רבי
מאיר. vekulan ro'in otam ke'ilu hem bnei chorin sheyardu minechaseihem shehem bnei
Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says in
terms of בושת, boshet we assess every person's בושת boshet. as if
they are wealthy people who have just lost their inheritance. That is,
they're wealthy people in terms of their stature, but they don't actually
have any property. Why? Because every Jewish person is a child of,
a descendant of אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov, and that gives
us all equal stature. And therefore, it obviously can't fit the Mishnah
because the Mishnah said it was very subjective, and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir has a very objective
singular standard. רבי יהודה אומר הגדול לפי גודלו והקטן לפי קטנו. Rabbi
Yehuda omer hagadol lefi godlo vehakatan lefi katno. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
takes a very subjective standard. He says a richer person or a
more prominent person is assessed on that and a less prominent person
is assessed based on that, and it's more embarrassing if you embarrass
someone very prominent or very famous than if you would embarrass someone
who nobody knows. Okay, רבי שמעון אומר עשירים רואין אותם כאילו הם
בני חורין שירדו מנכסיהם. Rabbi Shimon omer ashirim ro'in otam ke'ilu hem
bnei chorin sheyardu minechaseihem. According to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, rich people,
wealthy people, we assess them as if they are free people who
have just lost all of their money. That is, we treat them
at a low standard of what it means to be a rich
person. That is, we don't really take into account the fact that
you're wealthy. However, עניים כפחותים שבהם, aniyim kepchutim shebahem, and poor people
we assess them as if they're the poorest of the poor. That
is, they're basically two gradations and we bump you down to a
very low level. Like I said previously many times, this is based
on a principle that in court we have to use a very
high threshold burden of proof. So we can at most extract a
minimal amount from a person because we have the principle המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. If you want to prove it,
you have to be able to prove. The burden of proof is
on a person coming to extract money. So that's going to be
a limitation in terms of how much we can actually impose in
terms of this בושת. boshet. So מני? mani? אי רבי מאיר מתניתין
קתני הכל לפי המבייש והמתבייש. ei Rabbi Meir matnitin katani hakol lefi
hamivayesh vehamitbayesh.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir obviously doesn't fit. the משנה Mishnah because
the משנה Mishnah had said it goes based on who got embarrassed
and who did the embarrassing. For רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir כולהו כחד
הדדי נינהו. kulu kechad hadadeh ninhu. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
all the same standard for everybody. ואי רבי יהודה מתניתין קתני ve'ee
Rabbi Yehuda matnitin katani המבייש את הסומא חייב. hamivayesh et hasuma hayyav.
And it can't be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because the next משנה
Mishnah we're going to see on the next עמוד amud says if
you embarrass a blind person you are חייב, chayav. you're obligated.
But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the one who says a blind
person does not receive בושת. boshet, אלא לאו רבי שמעון היא, ela
lo Rabbi Shimon hee, it must be רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אפילו
תימא רבי יהודה, afilu tima Rabbi Yehuda, maybe you could say it
is
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. כי אמר רבי יהודה סומא אין לו בושת
kee amar Rabbi Yehuda suma ein lo boshet למשקל מיניה, lemishkal minei,
to extract בושת boshet from him. If a blind person embarrasses someone
else, then you don't make him pay בושת. boshet אבל למיתבא ליה
יהבינן ליה, aval limtava lei yahavinan lei, but if a blind person
got embarrassed by someone else, the blind person actually can collect בושת.
boshet So it works only in one direction according to רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. Okay. והא דתני סיפא veha de'tani seifa המבייש את הישן
חייב hamivayesh et hayashen hayyav
and the סיפא seifa of the next משנה Mishnah says if you
embarrass someone while they're asleep, you're obligated to pay. וישן שביייש פטור,
veyashen she'biyesh patur, but if you're sleeping and while you were asleep
you did something that embarrassed someone, I can imagine the person, you
roll over in bed and you pull the sheet off someone and
they're lying there naked in front of their friends and everyone laughs
at them. Okay. So וישן שביייש פטור, veyashen she'biyesh patur, you're exempt
in that case because בושת, boshet to be obligated to pay בושת
boshet you have to have כוונה לבייש, kavana livayesh, you have to
have intention to do something embarrassing.
אדם מועד לעולם adam muad l'olam for נזיקין, nezikin, exactly. Right, so
for בושת boshet, you don't say אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad l'olam.
Okay. ולא תני סומא שביייש פטור velo tani suma she'biyesh patur מכלל
דלא שנא הכא ולא שנא הכא. miklal delo shna hacha velo shna
hacha.
So no, this seems to prove against reading רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that way because a סומא, suma, a blind person, it doesn't say
one way פטור patur one way חייב like the way the משנה
Mishnah had distinguished between a sleeping person. And therefore, אלא מחוורתא מתניתין
רבי שמעון היא. ela mechavarta matnitin Rabbi Shimon hee. It must be
that the משנה Mishnah is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's the only
possibility because it doesn't fit רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it doesn't fit
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because it doesn't fit his שיטה shita about
a blind person, and therefore it must be רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon opinion seemed difficult to fit with the way
the משנה Mishnah, was. That is, the משנה Mishnah said it's all
based on who the person did the embarrassing and who the person
got embarrassed. According to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we bump everyone down
to the lowest bracket of, if you're rich, you're bumped down to
the lowest rich person's bracket, and if you're poor, we bump you
down to the lowest poor person's bracket. So it's a little bit
different between them, but it's basically a way of telling us how
to read the משנה, Mishnah. read it like the way רבי שמעון's
Rabbi Shimon שיטה shita is. Unless of course the משנה Mishnah. were
really a fourth position, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to suggest
that. They want to suggest that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is the
משנה. Mishnah So מאן תנא להא? man tana la'ha? How do you
embarrass a sleeping person? How do you embarrass, you could, a person
is sound asleep and they stay asleep. They stay asleep, how do
they know they were embarrassed? Well that's exactly the point. המבייש את
הישן חייב. hamivayesh et hayashen hayyav. You embarrass someone who's asleep, nonetheless
you're still חייב. Why? Suppose a person was asleep and this is
a thing people do nowadays, someone is asleep and they draw on
their face at summer camp or something like that, or you put
whipped cream in their hand and they go like this, right? So
a person is sound asleep, but they've done something, you've did something
to them that was embarrassing while they were asleep. If they had
been awake they would have been embarrassed. Of course, it's not about
whether as we're going to see, it's going to come up in
the next עמוד amud is it's not only about, we have to
keep going but we're going to see, it's not just about whether
or not the person himself was embarrassed, it's about how society experiences
the embarrassment as a whole. Okay. So מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן?
man tana la'ha de'tanu rabbanan? נתכוין לבייש את הקטן ובייש את הגדול
נותן לגדול מבושתו של קטן. nitkaven livayesh et hakatan uvayesh et hagadol
noten lagadol miboshto shel katan.
If you had intention to embarrass a minor, a child, and instead
you ended up doing something that embarrassed an adult, so you pay
to the adult the amount of money that you meant to have
to obligate yourself to to embarrass the child. That is, you pay
a lesser amount because it has to still be based on your
כוונה, kavana, it has to be based on what you intended to
do. Okay. לבייש את העבד ובייש בן חורין, livayesh et ha'eved uvayesh
ben chorin,
if you intended to embarrass a slave and you ended up embarrassing
a free person by accident, נותן לבן חורין דמי בושתו של עבד.
noten laben chorin d'mei boshto shel eved. You pay the free person
the amount of money you would be obligated to pay for embarrassing
the slave. So מאן היא? manee? Who is this? לא רבי מאיר
ולא רבי יהודה ולא רבי שמעון. lo Rabbi Meir velo Rabbi Yehuda
velo Rabbi Shimon. It doesn't fit any of those three positions. So
קא סלקא דעתך kalka da'atach קטן קטן בנכסים katan katan binchasim גדול
גדול בנכסים. gadol gadol binchasim.
So we, maybe it means קטן katan means someone who has very
few possessions and גדול gadol means someone with many possessions, a rich
person, a poor person, a rich person, not a child and an
adult. Okay, so אי רבי מאיר הא אמר כולהו כחד הדדי נינהו.
ee Rabbi Meir ha'amar kulu kechad hadadei ninhu. It can't be רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir for he says everyone is the same level. ואי
רבי יהודה דאמר אין לעבדים בושת, ve'ee Rabbi Yehuda de'amar ein la'avadim
boshet, and it can't be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda thinks that slaves have no בושת boshet at all because
we know their general sense that the way an עבד כנעני eved
kena'ani is seen by הלכה halakhah often is that עבדא בהפקירא ניחא
ליה, eved behefkeira nicha lei, slaves live a very promiscuous lifestyle, perhaps
there's no sense of embarrassment for the slaves, things like that. Or
not in the sense that they wouldn't be embarrassed at a personal
level, but the way society sees them, nothing would be embarrassing in
public if you're a slave. That's the s-. Okay, according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda ורבי שמעון דאמר נתכוון לבייש זה ובייש זה פטור
ve-Rabbi Shimon de-amar nitkavein levayesh zeh u-vayesh zeh patur
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is the one who said if you
intended to embarrass one person and you ended up embarrassing someone else
by accident you're totally exempt because it has to go entirely based
on your כוונה. kavanah. So then it can't fit any of those
three. So מאי טעמא דקטלא מה קטלא עד דמכוין ליה? mai ta'ama
de-katla mah katla ad de-michavein lei?
So maybe you should compare it to a case of murder. If
I went to murder someone, it only counts as murder if I
killed the person who I meant to kill. That's what's called in
Latin, right, mens rea. You had the thought of doing that crime.
You have to have a premeditation to make it murder. Okay. So
you had to have planned who you were planning to kill. דכתיב
וארב לו וקם עליו dich'tiv ve-arav lo ve-kam alav because he was
crouching in wait for him to try to attack him. That's from
the discussion of the manslaughter versus murder. What's the difference between manslaughter
and murder? Manslaughter you had no premeditation, you had no intent to
kill this person. That's part of the defining characteristic. עד דמכוין ליה.
ad de-michavein lei. You had to have intent for it. בושת נמי
עד דמכוין ליה. boshet nami ad de-michavein lei. So for בושת boshet
as well, so we see בושת boshet, interestingly חז"ל Hazal and of
course later sources pick up on it, compare the act of בושת,
boshet. embarrassing someone, very much to the act of murder. That is
we know המלבין פני חבירו ברבים חייב מיתה, ha-malbin penei chaveiro ba-rabim
chayav mitah,
the obviously hyperbolic statement, perhaps not so hyperbolic, but that embarrassing a
person in public is equivalent to actually killing them. זה שופך דמים.
zeh shofech damim. You've taken the blood out of their face because
they bleach white out of embarrassment, so it's the same kind of
action. Okay. Okay. בושת נמי עד דמכוין ליה. boshet nami ad de-michavein
lei. So
you have to have intention. And that's where we learn it from.
We learn the fact that בושת boshet, requires intention from the comparison
to the difference between murder and manslaughter, that is embarrassing someone is
more comparable to murder than manslaughter. And therefore if you embarrass someone
without intent, unintentionally, it doesn't count. Okay. דכתיב ושלחה ידה והחזיקה במבושיו.
dich'tiv ve-shalcha yadah ve-hechezika bi-mivushav.
One of the פסוקים pesukim we learn בושת boshet. from is a
case there are two men fighting and the wife of one of
them comes and tries to defend her husband by attacking his attacker,
and the way she attacks him is somehow revealing him in public
or something involved injuring him in the genital region. And in that
way, עד דמכוין ליה. ad de-michavein lei. She had to have the
intention to do that because she actually stuck out her hand and
did that. Okay. לעולם רבי יהודה. le-olam Rabbi Yehuda. So no, that
ברייתא braita has to be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and we have
to explain how it can fit with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda had said אין לעבדים בושת, ein la-avadim boshet,
now we have to explain. דכי קאמר רבי יהודה אין לעבדים בושת,
de-ki ka-amar Rabbi Yehuda ein la-avadim boshet, what does it mean when
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that slaves do not have the rights
to their embarrassment? למיתבא להו אבל למישם שיימינן בהו. le-meit'va le-hu aval
le-meisham sha-iminan be-hu.
So slaves are not given the monetary rights to their embarrassment, but
in terms of assessment, in terms of the calculation of בושת, boshet
slaves actually would have the calculation of בושת. boshet. That is, the
question of אין לעבדים בושת ein la-avadim boshet gets into the question
of who has the rights to the בושת, boshet? but it doesn't
mean that a slave has no financial assessment for how much it
would cost for them to be embarrassed. And therefore what happened? You
tried to embarrass
the slave and you ended up embarrassing a free person. You pay
the free person the money based on how much you would pay
embarrassment for a slave. So you're using the assessment of a slave
to pay to a free person, and that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda was talking about and that fits with רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's
שיטה. shita. Okay. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, alternatively, אפילו תימא רבי מאיר.
afilu teima Rabbi Meir.
Maybe you could say it's even רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. מי סבר
גדול גדול בנכסים קטן קטן בנכסים? mi savar gadol gadol bi-nechasim katan
katan bi-nechasim? No, who said that גדול gadol means a rich person
and קטן katan means a poor person? לא גדול ממש קטן ממש.
lo gadol mamash katan mamash. No,
גדול means an adult and קטן katan means a child. And it
could fit with רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position as well. Because even
though רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said everyone is on the same standing
because we're all בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב, benei Avraham Yitzchak ve-Ya'akov, we're
all the descendants of our ancestors who were very high level, nonetheless
that would apply differently to adults and children. Obviously רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, even though he has a flat playing field in terms of
adults, he wouldn't say that adults and children are equal regarding
בושת. boshet, Okay. וקטן בר בושת הוא? ve-katan bar boshet hu? Is
a קטן, katan, is a child really someone who you would assess
their בושת boshet for? כדאמר רב פפא דמכלמי ליה ומיכלם. ke-de-amar Rav
Pappa de-machalmei lei u-michlam. So רב פפא Rav Pappa said yes, there
are cases where children could be embarrassed. The kind of embarrassment a
child could suffer is that if you would tell a child this
and they would actually be embarrassed, they would feel hurt by that,
then that is something that actually you would be able to assess
the בושת. boshet That is, there are certain children who are young
enough or certain things that roll off kids' backs in a way
that adults might take more seriously and which would be worth nothing
for a child, and there are older kids or types of embarrassment
that would affect children. And there are ways in that sense, so
רב פפא Rav Pappa said you have to assess based on דמכלמי
ליה ומיכלם. de-machalmei lei u-michlam. הכא נמי דמכלמי ליה ומיכלם. hacha nami
de-machalmei lei u-michlam. So too here, drawing attention to the fact that
he was embarrassed. Like actually if you point out, right. Well or
the point is that when does a child have בושת? boshet. When
the child experiences the embarrassment of having been
embarrassed. בושת, boshet the financial calculation will be applied if embarrassment, the
emotion, is felt. It's דמכלמי ליה ומכלם. de-makhlimu leh u-makhlam. They are...
they are drawing his attention to. Perhaps? I'm not sure if it's...
I think it means more like if you would go up to
a kid comparable to this kid and tell him the same thing
that he would be embarrassed, something like that. That's... that's just their
benchmark for calculating that. Okay, the next משנה. We'll try to keep...
we'll go as far as we can. The משנה says: המבייש את
הערום, ha-mevayyesh et ha-arum,
if you embarrass someone who is naked, המבייש את הסומא ha-mevayyesh et
ha-suma or you embarrass someone who is blind, והמבייש את הישן ve-ha-mevayyesh
et ha-yashen or you embarrass someone who is asleep, חייב, you're liable
for all those kinds of embarrassment. וישן שביייש, ve-yashen she-biyyesh,
but a person who is asleep who embarrasses someone else, פטור, patur,
that person is exempt. נפל מן הגג, nafal min ha-gag, a person
fell off the roof והזיק ve-hizzik and caused damage וביייש u-biyyesh and
made someone embarrassed. Okay, חייב על הנזק ופטור על הבושת hayyav al
ha-nezek u-patur al ha-boshet עד שיהא מתכוון. ad she-yehe mitkavven.
So that's the same principle, that is, a person who fell off
the roof by accident, obviously, and they damaged something and they embarrassed
someone, then they pay for the נזק, nezek, they pay for the
damage because אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad le-olam, but they don't pay
for the בושת boshet. because בושת boshet you have to have כוונה.
kavvanah. And that was quoted already, if you could look on the
side, that's on the גמרא Gemara on כז עמוד א. Kaf Zayin
Amud Alef. It came up when we were discussing נזק, nezek so
now here נזק comes up when we're discussing בושת. boshet The גמרא
Gemara says: תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, ביישו ערום חייב, biyyesho arum hayyav,
ואינו דומה ביישו ערום לביישו לבוש. ve-eno domeh biyyesho arum le-biyyesho lavush.
So not... even though a person who embarrasses someone while they're naked
is liable, it's nowhere near as embarrassing as embarrassing someone while they're
clothed. That's the idea. And obviously, what kind of בושת boshet. are
we talking about? Presumably, it has some to do with... with being
undressed in public or undressed in front of people who you feel
you should be dressed in front of. So that's the difference, is
that if a person is wearing their clothes and then you take
their clothes off, that would be very embarrassing. If a person is...
is sort of partially naked already and then you reveal them even
more, it'll be less embarrassing. It will still be embarrassing. So ביישו
בבית המרחץ חייב. biyyesho be-veit ha-merhatz hayyav. If you embarrass someone at
the bathhouse, you're liable. ואינו דומה ביישו בבית המרחץ לביישו בשוק. ve-eno
domeh biyyesho be-veit ha-merhatz le-biyyesho ba-shuk.
And there's no comparison. Obviously, it's much more embarrassing to be embarrassed
in the... in the marketplace than it is to be embarrassed in
the bathhouse. That is, in a locker room you expect that people
are going around naked or people are in a partial undress. Nonetheless,
to be embarrassed in that way in the marketplace would be much...
much more embarrassing. What kind of כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot is that,
as if a person's wearing שעטנז shaatnez or not wearing שעטנז? shaatnez?
So for שעטנז דרבנן shaatnez de-rabbanan you don't rip off their clothing.
So the גמרא Gemara discusses that. The question of wearing שעטנז דרבנן
shaatnez de-rabbanan in the... in the... I think it's in ברכות. Berakhot.
Is that a person who's wearing שעטנז shaatnez that's only שעטנז מדרבנן,
shaatnez mi-de-rabbanan, they're allowed to continue wearing it and they don't have
to take it off in the street because of כבוד הבריות, kevod
ha-beriyot, because כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot recognizes that a person being embarrassed
in such a way, being naked in the marketplace, would be too
much to ask. But if it's שעטנז דאורייתא, shaatnez de-oraita, you actually
do have to take it off because of the principle. So in
terms of how many knots are attaching the wool to the linen
and things like that, if it was one knot or two knots
or one stitch or two stitches, things like that. So כבוד הבריות
kevod ha-beriyot trumps שעטנז דרבנן. shaatnez de-rabbanan. Exactly.
The גמרא's Gemara principle is a little bit confusing. People often take
it out of... or misapply it. It says: כבוד הבריות דוחה לא
תעשה שבתורה. kevod ha-beriyot doheh lo taaseh she-ba-torah. That
כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot overrides a negative prohibition in the Torah. In
the singular. What does that mean? Does that mean it violates any
negative prohibition in the Torah? No. It seems the way that that's
applied by many of the ראשונים is it overrides one specific לא
תעשה lo taaseh in the Torah, which is the לא תעשה lo
taaseh לא תסור, lo tasur, which means to follow rabbinic decrees. And
therefore what it really means is that... what it really... again, the
rabbis often speak in a kind of a code. We have to
figure out, we have to rely on... on interpretation.
So that sense is that כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot should override rabbinic
rules in cases... and the כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot again, what kind
of things are כבוד הבריות? kevod ha-beriyot? Needing to bring something to
wipe with to the bathroom on שבת or שעטנז דרבנן shaatnez de-rabbanan
being clothed in the street, things that really have to do with
very intimate aspects of a person being naked or having a certain
bodily function, bodily needs.
Many people nowadays try to apply כבוד הבריות... kevod ha-beriyot... everything becomes
כבוד הבריות, kevod ha-beriyot, everything that's embarrassing is כבוד הבריות. kevod ha-beriyot.
Obviously, it's not the way חז"ל used it. You have to look
in the גמרא Gemara and see... see what kinds of things fall
into that category. Just because they use the phrase "it's only rabbinic."
Only rabbinic. I hear it all the time and then... Well, there
are many... but the other side that says "but the rabbis are
supposed to be as serious as the Torah." So there are many
principles in the גמרא Gemara and in הלכה that can mitigate a
rabbinic prohibition but are not powerful enough to mitigate what's a biblical
prohibition because the rabbis said, you know, הם אמרו והם אמרו. hem
ameru ve-hem ameru. The rabbis have the power to provide the parameters
for their גזירה gezeirah and their laws. So rabbinic laws are often
a little bit more flexible in terms of certain kinds of mitigating
circumstances. So it depends. A lot has been written about that. You
know, perhaps the biggest... I mean, it's like a meta-topic in הלכה
of how do... we're getting ahead... Okay. So, אנה ואשוויה בבית המרחץ
ואשוויה בבית המושב. anah va'ashvei beveit hamerchatz va'ashvei beveit hamoshav. Okay. אמר
מר. amar mar. באשו אדם חייב. ba'asho adam chayav. So, so
the ברייתא had said, if you embarrass someone while they're naked, you're
חייב. ערום בר בושת הוא? arum bar boshet hu? Is a person
who's already naked someone who could be embarrassed? Meaning, the fact that
you're naked in front of someone else means you sort of don't
already—you don't have so much בושת. boshet. You're not going to be
so embarrassed. So that's the question. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav
Pappa, מאי ערום? mai arum? What does it mean ערום arum that
you were naked? דאתי זיקא וכרכיה למאניה. da'ati zika vecharchei lemanei.
The wind came and blew your clothes up. Again, remember, men back
in the time of the גמרא Gemara used to wear like a
long smock type of a robe-shirt type thing. So the wind could
lift that up. People didn't wear underwear back then. And so ואתא
הוא ודלינהו טפי ובישו. ve'ata hu vedalineihu tefei uveisho.
And then someone else, once the wind has come and blown up
your robe, and then someone comes and pulls it even more. So
they—you were as if already naked and they made that experience even
more embarrassing by revealing even more of you at that time. So
ביישו בבית המרחץ חייב. beisho beveit hamerchatz chayav. To be embarrassed in
the bathhouse? בבית המרחץ בר בושת הוא? beveit hamerchatz bar boshet hu?
Is it embarrassing to be in the locker room? It's not embarrassing.
Everybody's changing. Everybody's naked in the locker room or in the sauna
or something like that. So אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa שביישו
על גב הנהר. shebeisho al gav hanahar. No, it doesn't mean in
the מרחץ merchatz in a closed private bathhouse. It means you were
bathing by the river and someone came and embarrassed you. They said,
"Hey look, it's פלוני, Ploni, he's down by the river and he's
naked and he's swimming." So that's the difference. And that's why it
would be embarrassing because it's semi-public, semi-private. It's not a closed bathhouse
where the person feels protected or feels like they have some dignity.
Okay. בעי רבי אבא בר ממל, ba'ei Rabbi Abba bar Memel, ביישו
ישן ומת. beisho yashen umet. What happens if you embarrass a person
while they're asleep and then the person dies in their sleep? So
the point is the person never experienced the בושת boshet. themselves. They
never experienced that embarrassment themselves. The question is whether or not the
person is obligated to pay for the בושת boshet? to their heirs
or not. We're going to see. So מאי קא מיבעי ליה? mai
ka miba'ei lei? So אמר רב זביד, amar Rav Zvid, הכי קא
מיבעי ליה. hachi ka miba'ei lei. This is the question. משום כיסופא
הוא? mishum kisufa hu? Is it כיסופא? kisufa? Look in רש"י. Rashi.
So רש"י Rashi says, חפיית פנים. chapiyat panim. It's embarrassment to the
person himself. It's some kind of distress that they feel in their
emotional state. Okay. והא מית ליה דלית ליה. veha mit lei deleit
lei.
And this person dies, so he doesn't have any emotional response to
this embarrassment. כיסופא. kisufa. או דילמא משום זילותא הוא? o dilma mishum
ziluta hu?
Maybe it's זילותא. ziluta. זילותא ziluta is a much broader sense of
embarrassment. Look in רש"י. Rashi. זילותא דמזלזל ביה בפני רבים. ziluta demizalzel
bei bifnei rabbim. That is,
it's the experience of having embarrassed this person in front of other
people. That is, it's not about whether or not the person feels
embarrassed. It's a societal standard in terms of what does it mean
to be embarrassed. And that's a question. והא עוזליה. veha ozlei. You
still were מזלזל mizalzel this person while they were alive, even though
they never experienced the embarrassment themselves. Their person, their stature in society
was reduced because of what you did, whether or not they actually
felt the embarrassment. Okay. תא שמע. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer,
חרש וקטן יש להם בושת. cheresh vekatan yesh lahem boshet. A deaf
person and a child do have בושת. boshet That is, something embarrassing
could happen—you could embarrass them and you would be liable. שוטה אין
לו בושת. shoteh ein lo boshet. But a person who has, you
know, severe some kind of a mental illness or mental disability does
not have בושת. boshet The assumption being that a person who's not
aware of their place in society at all, basically can't experience בושת.
boshet. Obviously, I think nowadays the way any modern person who has
worked with people who have mental disabilities or things like that understands
that many people even who have—I think most people with mental disabilities
nowadays based on our society would not fall into the category that
the גמרא Gemara calls שוטה. shoteh. Because a שוטה shoteh is someone
who really does totally irrational things, doesn't have any awareness of what
they're doing. Most people nowadays, even if they have a disability or
if they have special needs and things like that, those are people
who are still aware of their place in society. They're still aware
of who they are. Obviously, they can be embarrassed. It's a very
different kind of person than what the גמרא calls a שוטה. shoteh.
This is important to note. Okay. שוטה אין לו בושת. shoteh ein
lo boshet. So איבעית אימא. iba'it eima. יאמר בשלמא? yomar bishlama? Right.
Sorry. אי אמרת בשלמא ei amrat bishlama משום זילותא. mishum ziluta.
If you're going to say it's because of their place in society
that they would become embarrassed, היינו דקתני קטן. hainu deka-tani katan. That's
why it says קטן. katan. Because קטן katan doesn't have כיסופא kisufa
in the same way. קטן katan is not going to feel the
personal embarrassment the same way. Or we don't care as much because
children, whatever, kids, kids make fun of each other all the time.
It rolls off their backs in a different way. Or, I mean,
again it depends on the psychology of it. But the sense that
a person's standing in society is not going to be hampered so
much. That's why it comes to teach קטן. katan. אלא אי אמרת
משום כיסופא, ela ei amrat mishum kisufa, קטן בר בושת הוא? katan
bar boshet hu? But if you're going to say it's because of
כיסופא, kisufa, is a קטן katan really connected to that sense of
בושת? boshet. Because a קטן katan has much less personal sense of
worth that's going to be damaged by this embarrassment. Okay.
Ah, so we're going to see. אלא מאי משום זילותא, Ela mai
mishum ziluta, maybe you'll say it's because of זילותא, ziluta, it's because
of their societal standing. אפילו שוטה נמי, Afilu shoteh nami, but then
you would say a שוטה shoteh as well, a שוטה shoteh still
has a sense of how their place in society would be affected
by having been embarrassed. That is, for even the גמרא's שוטה shoteh
that's someone who's totally unaware of their standing,
it's still embarrassing for the people around them if they've been embarrassed
by someone
else. Okay. So אמרי שוטה אין לך בושת גדול מזו. shoteh ein
lach boshet gadol mizo. That is, there's a suggestion that to be
a שוטה shoteh already is very embarrassing for society, that is their
family members perhaps or the people who live near them, they already
have a sense of what that means, that that was embarrassing for
them. Therefore, there's no additional בושת boshet. to be calculated. Okay. מכל
מקום Mikol makom נפשוט מינה דמשום זילותא הוא, nifshot minah demishum ziluta
hu, so
maybe we should still extract from this that the assessment of בושת
boshet? should be based on זילותא, ziluta, based on the person's societal
standing in society. דאי
משום כיסופא קטן בר כיסופא הוא? De'i mishum kisufa katan bar kisufa
hu? Are you going to say it's because of כיסופא, kisufa, it's
because a person a קטן katan doesn't have that kind of personal
awareness? דאמר רב פפה, De'amar Rav Pappa,
no, it must be like רב פפה Rav Pappa said, exactly like
Hillel suggested. רב פפה Rav Pappa said דמכלימו ליה ומכלם. demachlimu lei
umichlam. So רב פפה Rav Pappa said even a קטן katan could
have כיסופא, kisufa, could have that personal sense of hurt, based on
the fact that a קטן katan is aware of the kinds of
things that could be embarrassing, but at a certain age. A two-year-old
is different than an eight-year-old, eight-year-old is different than a twelve-year-old. So
those kinds of things are going to provide a sliding scale. הכא
נמי דמכלימו ליה ומכלם, Hacha nami demachlimu lei umichlam, so too, we
here we should assess it for a קטן katan if it's something
that the person the child would be embarrassed by, that would be
something that you would calculate בושת. boshet. רב פפה אמר הכי קמיבעיא
ליה: Rav Pappa amar hachi kamibaiya lei: משום כיסופא דידיה, Mishum kisufa
didei, is it based on his own embarrassment? ומהאיס ליה, Vahamis lei,
and then this person has already died. או דילמא משום בושת משפחה,
O dilma mishum boshet mishpacha, or is it based on embarrassment to
the family, the family at whole? That is, even if it's based
on כיסופא kisufa and we're willing to include a קטן katan based
on כיסופא kisufa according to רב פפה, Rav Pappa, nonetheless, is it
the person's personal sense or is it for their whole family? That's
a little bit wider. תא שמע: חרש וקטן יש להם בושת, cheresh
vekatan yesh lahem boshet,
a child and a deaf person do have בושת. boshet שוטה אין
בו בושת, Shoteh ein bo boshet, and a שוטה shoteh does not
have בושת. אי אמרת בשלמא משום בושת משפחה, Ei amrat bishlama mishum
boshet mishpacha, if you're going to say it's because of the family,
היינו דקתני קטן, hainu dektani katan, that's why it says קטן, katan,
that is a קטן katan doesn't have a personal sense of value
but for their whole family it would be embarrassed. אלא אי אמרת
משום כיסופא דידיה, Ela ei amrat mishum kisufa didei, קטן בר בושת
הוא? katan bar boshet hu? Are we going to say that a
קטן katan has בושת? אלא מאי משום בושת דבני משפחה, Ela mai
mishum boshet debnei mishpacha, it must be because of for the family.
אפילו שוטה נמי, Afilu shoteh nami, so for a שוטה shoteh then
we would include it even for the family of the שוטה shoteh
we would say that a שוטה shoteh also has בושת. שוטה אין
לך בושת גדול מזו. Shoteh ein lach boshet gadol mizo. The suggestion
that for the family there's still a certain amount of בושת for
the family to have a שוטה shoteh in their family already, and
therefore, to that extent, there would be no extension
extension if
the
שוטה shoteh were to be
embarrassed. Okay. מכל מקום נפשוט מינה דמשום בושת משפחה, Mikol makom nifshot
minah demishum boshet mishpacha, דאי משום כיסופא קטן בר כיסופא
הוא? de'i mishum kisufa katan bar kisufa hu? Is a קטן בר
כיסופא? katan bar kisufa? אמר רב פפה, Amar Rav Pappa, אין, דמכלימו
ליה ומכלם. demachlimu lei umichlam.
So רב פפה Rav Pappa again, the suggestion of רב פפה, Rav
Pappa, a child's embarrassment even at the
personal level could be assessed based on how they how they could
feel it even at the personal level and we don't have to
extend it to the stronger broader sense of זילותא ziluta or of
embarrassment to society, it could even be assessed at the personal level.
And that was פה
ע"א. Peh-Heh Amud Alef. We'll pick up there tomorrow with the next
דף. daf. Let's go.